Register of the Jay Lovestone papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jay Lovestone papers
1904-1989
75091
Hoover Institution Archives
896 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 49 envelopes, 3 sound tape reels, 1 framed map (364.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, bulletins, clippings, serial issues, pamphlets, other printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings relating to the Communist International, the communist movement in the United States and elsewhere, communist influence in American and foreign trade unions, and organized labor movements in the United States and abroad. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Lovestone, Jay.
Access
Collection open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of some sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1907 or 1908 Moved to the United States
1913-1915 In his early teens, became interested in the DeLeonite Socialist Labor Party and shortly thereafter joined the Socialist Party.
1914-1918 Attended City College of New York and became a member of the Socialist Study Club, which was affiliated with the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. In 1917, became president of the Society's branch at C.C.N.Y.
1918 Graduated, City College of New York
1918-1920 Held a number of jobs and at various times attended classes at the City College of Accounting, New York University Law School, and Columbia University.
1919 Helped to organize the left wing sections of the pro-Communists in New York. Later became delegate to the founding convention of the American Communist Party. [Note: The American Communist Party underwent several reorganizations and name changes during the time Jay Lovestone was a member. Please see Series description for further information.] He was elected to the Program Committee and the First Central Executive Committee.
1921 Assistant Secretary, Communist Party
1922 National Secretary, Communist Party
1923 Author of The Government - Strikebreaker, a study of government intervention in the strikes of 1921-1922.
1925 Organization Secretary, Communist Party
1927 General Secretary, Communist Party
1929 Ousted from Communist Party by Joseph Stalin.
1929-1940 Founder and head of Communist Party Opposition known as Lovestoneites or Lovestone Group. [Note: The Communist Party Opposition underwent several name changes during the time Jay Lovestone headed the group. Please see Series description for further information.]
1942-1944 Committee to Defend America - Citizens for Victory
1944-1956 Director, International Ladies Garment Workers Union (ILGWU), Political Department Director, International Affairs Department Executive Secretary, American Federation of Labor (AFL), Free Trade Union Committee
1956-1963 Director of International Publications, American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) Assistant Director of International Affairs Department, AFL-CIO
1963-1974 Director of International Affairs Department, AFL-CIO
1974-1990 Consultant on International Affairs, ILGWU and AFL-CIO
1990 March 7 Died, New York City
Arrangement
Arranged into two groups: an original accession, Boxes 1-695, and an increment of additional materials, Boxes 696-899. Within the two groups, materials are arranged in series by physical form or topic.
The original accession is arranged in the following series: Printed Material; Biographical File; Communist Party, U.S.A.; Communist Party (Opposition); Office Files; Correspondence; Subject File; Speeches and Writings; German Language Material; Unprocessed Newspapers, Magazine Clippings and Photocopies of Clippings; Address Label Masters for Mailing List; Memorabilia; Damaged Material; Map; Sound Recordings; and Photographs.
The increment of additional materials is arranged in the following series: Correspondence; Speeches and Writings; Other Unpublished Material; Sound Recording; Photographs and Postcards; Printed Biographical File; Printed Subject File; and Memorabilia.
Additionally, there is a Declassified U.S. Government Records series, which contains materials from both groups.
Location of Original Materials
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
AFL-CIO.; American Federation of Labor. Free Trade Union Committee.; Communist International.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Communist Party, U.S.A. (Opposition); Audiotapes.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Labor movement--United States.; Labor movement.; Trade-unions and communism.; Trade-unions--United States.; Trade-unions.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Politics and government.
- PRINTED MATERIAL, 1911-1977 (Boxes 1-191)
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by title or author.
  - A la lumiere du marxisme, Essais - Sciences Physico-Mathematiques, Sciences Naturelles, Sciences Humaines, 1935 (Box 1)
  - AALC Reporter, a publication of the African-American Labor Center, 1971 January, 1974 April
  - The ABM and the Changed Strategic Military Balance, U.S.A. vs. U.S.S.R., study prepared by the National Strategy Committee of the American Security Council, 1969 May
  - ABN Correspondence, monthly bulletin of the Antibolshevik Bloc of Nations, 1960 July-August
  - ACI bulletin quotidien de l'Agence Cooperative D'Information (Daily Bulletin of the Cooperative Information Agency), 1961 June 4
  - A.I. Labor Letter, American Income Life Insurance Company, 1975 January
  - ASC Broadcast Briefs, a publication of the American Security Council, 1969 March
    See also: listing under American Security Council.
  - ASC Newsletter, a publication of the American Security Council (incomplete), 1962 January 31 - 1963 January 31
  - A.S.O. (Alianza Sindical Obrera de Espana), 1964 August, October, 1968 January
  - Abbott, Charles C., The International Position and Commitments of the United States, No. 449 in the series "National Economic Problems,", 1953
  - Absolute Truth, The (photographs of World War I)
  - Academy of Political Science, Proceedings, "The Soviet Union Since Khrushchev--New Trends and Old Problems,", 1965 April
  - Accord, "The European Syndicalist Student Movement,", 1968 March
  - Acheson, Dean, Fifty Years After, 1961
  - Adams, James Truslow, An American Looks at the British Empire, 1940
  - Adams, John Clarke, A Report on the Semester in Italy, 1960
  - L'Adunata dei Refrattari, 1928 December
  - Advance, The, published by the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 1937 October, 1966 June
  - Africa, The World Today Series, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Africa League, A New American Policy Toward Africa, 1960
  - Africa Opinion (incomplete), 1961 July - 1962 May
  - Africa South, 1956 October-December
  - Africa Today, 1959 January-February
  - Africa Weekly, 1959 May
  - African-American Labor Center, publications (incomplete), 1965-1970
  - African Comment (incomplete), 1963-1966
  - African Labour News (incomplete), 1963-1964
  - African Review (incomplete), 1968-1976
  - African Survey, 1963 June
  - Afro-Asian Institute for Labour Studies and Co-operation, undated
  - Afro-Asian Labour Bulletin, 1966 April, 1973 May
  - Air-Terre-Mer (Air, Land, Sea), 1951 May
  - Der aktuelle Osten, Kommentare und Nachrichten aus Politik, Wirtschaft und Technik der UdSSR und der Ubrigen Lander des RGW (COMECON) (incomplete) (Boxes 3-4)
  - Aktuelle Probleme des Imperialismus, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Alba, Victor, La America Latina y los Congresos del Partido Comunista Ruso, circa 1959
  - Alexandrov, K., China's Independent Foreign Policy, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Alexandrow, Dimitriji, Kommunismus in der Krise, undated
  - Algeria, Permanent Mission to the United Nations, Information Bulletin, 1964 May 1
  - Algeria, Questions and Answers, The Algerian Office, 1960
  - Algerian Delegation, What is Algeria?, 1955 September
  - Algerian Front of National Liberation Delegation, The Question of Algeria, Background Document, The European Minority, circa 1957
  - Aliber, Robert Z., Choices for the Dollar, National Planning Association, 1969
  - Allen, Frederick Lewis, Only Yesterday, 2 vols., 1931
  - Allen, Harland H., The Businessman's Stake in American-Soviet Friendship, undated
  - Alliance for Labor Action, To Find Answers to the Urgent Problems of Our Society, 1968
  - Alliance for Progress, Latin American Growth Trends: Seven Years of the Alliance for Progress, 1968
  - Allnut, E. F., and Gerhard Leibholz, Re-Educating Germans?, 1944
  - Almanac, 1961
  - Almanach des Verlages der Kommunistischen Internationale, 1921
  - Alsop, Joseph, and Robert Kinter American White Paper, 1940
  - Alternative, Sozialistische Zeitschrift fur Politik, Wirtschaft und Kultur, 1966 June
  - Alternative, The, 1972 March, 1975 August-September
  - Amalgamated Engineering Union, Report of the Delegation to the U.S.A., 1949 March, April
  - Amalgamated Journal, The, Official Organ of the Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers, 1942 January 22
  - Ambassade de France, Service de Presse et d'Information, New York
    - France Aid and Cooperation, 1962 December
    - France and Its Armed Forces, 1964 December
    - France at the European Summit Conference, The Hague, 1969 December 1-2
  - America in Cifre, 1951 (Box 6)
  - America United, a radio forum conducted by the American Federation of Labor on "Should America Open Its Doors to Displaced Persons of Europe?,", 1947 April 6
  - American-African Affairs Associations, Red China in Africa, undated
  - American Assembly
    - Black Economic Development, 1969 April
    - Land Use in America, 1974 April
    - Law and a Changing Society II, 1975 June
    - The Multinational Corporation, 1974 December
    - The United States and Eastern Europe, 1967 April
  - American Association for Economic Freedom
    - Problems of the National Labor Relations Board, undated
    - Unemployment Must Be Abolished!, 1940 June
  - American Association for the United Nations
    - The Economic and Political Security of the New States of Africa and Asia, 1961 February
    - Strengthening the United Nations, 1957
    - We, the Peoples... A Brief History of the United Nations, 1945 October
  - American Bar Association, Brief on Communism: Marxism-Leninism, Its Aims, Purposes, Objectives and Practices, undated
  - American Bar Association, Section on International and Comparative Law, The Rule of Law in the United States, A Statement By the Committee to Cooperate with the International Commission of Jurists, 1958 February
  - American Bulletin, The, published by the Czechoslovak National Council of America (incomplete), 1965 November - 1976 November
  - American Cause, 1976 January-February
  - American Civil Liberties Union
    - Black Justice, 1931 May
    - Justice--North Carolina Style, 1930 May
  - American Committee for a Free Spanish Republic, Franco - War Criminal Allied with Hitler and Mussolini, undated
  - American Committee for Liberation
    - Communicating with the People Behind the Iron Curtain, 1957
    - Peaceful Co-Existence, What it Means to Khrushchev, circa 1960
    - Traditional Goals of Labour Movement Obliterated by Measures of Red China, undated
    - U.S. Is Dictatorship, Constitution a Fraud, USSR Population Told, undated
  - American Committee on Africa
    - Portugal in Africa, 1968 December
    - A Summary Report on the Bank Campaign, circa 1969
  - American Committee on United Europe, Euratom and the Common Market, 1956 December
  - American Council for Nationalities Service, American Abroad: Spokesman for the United States, 1959 February
  - American Council for Public Affairs, Total Defense, 1940 June
  - American Economic Review, The, 1929 September
  - American Employers and the International Labor Organization, undated
  - American Federation of Labor (Box 7)
    - The A.F. of L. at Work: Towards Democracy in Germany, 1947
    - La A.F.L., La Revolucion Guatemalteca Democratica y Los Communistas, 1954
    - A.F.L. News-Reporter, 1952 August 22
    - Die A.F. of L. Und die deutsche Arbeiterbewegung, 1952
    - America United, a radio forum conducted by the American Federation of Labor on "More TVAs?,", 1945
    - American Federation of Labor Weekly News Service (incomplete), 1942 September - 1950 March
    - American Labor and the World Crisis, 1952
    - American Labor Looks at the World
      - 1947 October
      - [No. II], 1948 November
      - [No. III], 1949 October
      - [No. IV], 1950 September
      - [No. V], 1951 September
      - [No. VI], 1952 September
      - [No. VII], 1953 September
      - [No. VIII], 1954 September
      - [No. IX], 1955 December
    - Consumer Cooperatives, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Directory of Affiliates and Constitution, 1954
    - For Peace and Freedom, 1953
    - Fur Freiheit, Arbeit und Frieden, undated
    - Great Tax Fraud, The, 1951
    - Here's the Answer, Fact Book on Key Legislation, 1950
    - Eine internationale Erklarung der Grundrechte, undated
    - Labor and Education in 1939
    - Labor League of Human Rights, Special Bulletin, 1946
    - Labor's Monthly Survey, 1939-1951
    - National Association of Manufacturers Exposed, Report of the Executive Council of the American Federation of Labor to the Seattle, Washington, Convention, 1913
    - Pacific Labour Proceedings
      - Convention, 1940
      - Convention, 1941
      - Convention, 1943
      - Convention, 1947
      - Convention, 1948 (Box 9)
      - Convention, 1949
      - Convention, 1951
      - Convention, 1952
    - Report of the Executive Council of the American Federation of Labor
      - Fifty-Sixth Annual Convention, 1936 November 16
      - Sixty-First Annual Convention, 1941 October 6
      - Sixty-Third Annual Convention, 1943 October 4
    - Research Report, 1948 October
    - The Rights of Labor, Democracy vs. Totalitarianism, 1947 October
    - Samuel Gompers Centennial Committee
      - The Gompers Story
      - Samuel Gompers' Credo
    - Stalin vs. Sun Yat-sen: The Truth about Life in Communist China, undated
    - Subsidized Industrial Migration, the Luring of Plants to New Locations, 1955
    - Toward a Reappraisal of American Foreign Policy and A Program of Action, 1954
    - We Saw Israel: A Report of a Visit by American Trade Unionists, undated
    - What Happened to the Trade Unions Behind the Iron Curtain, 1948
    - Who's Who in Communist China, by Wei Chen, 1954
    - Why Communist China Should Not Be Admitted to the United Nations, 1954
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) (Box 10)
    - The AFL-CIO and World Affairs, 1970
    - AFL-CIO News (incomplete), 1956-1970
    - The AFL-CIO Platform Proposals to the Republican and Democratic Conventions, 1964, 1968
    - American Federationist (incomplete), 1942 January - 1976 April
    - American Labor and World Affairs, undated
    - America's Health Needs, the Government's Role, undated
    - America's Responsibility for the Preservation of Human Freedom, 1959 (Box 11)
    - Automation, undated
    - Building and Construction Trades Bulletin, 1961 May
    - The Case for the Union Shop, undated
    - Civil Rights, in the AFL-CIO, 1961
    - Codes of Ethical Practices, 1958
    - Collective Bargaining Report, 1959 July, 1960 December
    - Constitution, 1965
    - Dedication of the Home of American Labor, 1956 June 4
    - The Disaffiliation of the UAW, 1968
    - Documents on Arms Control, undated
    - Economic Trends and Outlook, 1958 March, November, 1960 November
    - Education News and Views, 1956 June
    - Fact vs. Propaganda: The Truth about "Right to Work" Laws, 1958
    - For World Peace and Freedom, 1960 April
    - Foreign Aid for Peace and Freedom, 1963
    - Free Trade Union Committee, Slave Labor in the Soviet World, undated
    - Free Trade Union News
      - 1946-1949
      - 1950-1962 (Box 12)
      - 1963-1968 (Box 13)
      - 1969-1973 (Box 14)
      - 1974-1977 (Box 15)
    - The Greater Danger, 1956
    - Handbook on Hospital Insurance for the Aged through Social Security, 1963
    - Handbook on the Industrial Security Program of the Department of Defense, 1955
    - The History of 14 (b) and What It Means, undated
    - The House of Labor, 1957
    - IUD Agenda, 1965 November
    - I. U. D. Bulletin, 1959 July, 1960 January, 1972 November-December
    - The Industrial Union Department, undated (Box 16)
    - International Affairs Resolutions, 1967, 1969
    - Labor and Medical Care, undated
    - Labor and Politics, undated
    - Labor Fights the Enemies of Democracy, 1964
    - Labor Looks at Congress, 1967
    - Labor Looks at the 85th Congress, 1958
    - Labor Looks at the 86th Congress, 1960
    - Labor Looks at the 87th Congress, 1962
    - Labor Looks at the Nation's Economy, 1963
    - Labor's Economic Review (incomplete), 1956 April - 1960 August
    - Los Angeles Citizen, 1962 December 7
    - Memo to Congress: A Positive Program for America, 1960
    - The Merger of the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1955
    - Miscellaneous
    - News from the AFL-CIO
      - 1955-1962
      - 1963-1977 (Box 17)
    - News from the Industrial Union Department, 1960 (Box 18)
    - The Nixon Economic Program, 1972
    - Noticiero Obrero Norteamericano (North American Worker News), 1965 June 15
    - An Open Letter from the Executive Committee of the Union of African Students in the Soviet Union
    - Policy Resolutions, 1961, 1971
    - Policy Resolutions on International Affairs, 1959, 1961, 1963, 1965, 1967, 1969
    - Political Memo from COPE (incomplete), 1959-1977
    - Power for What?, undated
    - Preguntas y Respuestas: El Movimiento Obrero Norteamericano y Los Asuntos Interamericanos, 1959
    - Proceedings
      - Convention, 1955
      - Convention, 1961
      - Convention, 1963
      - Convention, 1965
      - Convention, 1967
      - Convention, 1973 (Box 19)
      - Convention, 1975
    - Program, International Affairs Conference, 1965 March 11-12
    - Questions and Answers on American Labor and World Affairs, 1960
    - Report of the AFL-CIO Executive Council, 1957, 1961, 1963, 1967, 1975
    - Resolutions
    - Resolutions on Collective Bargaining and Related Issues, 1955 (Box 20)
    - Resolutions on Foreign Policy, 1955
    - Samuel Gompers Centennial Committee, 1950
    - Security in Time of Need, 1969
    - Shorter Hours to Create Jobs, 1964
    - Speakers' Handbook, 1966
    - Staff Retirement Plan, 1958
    - Statements and Reports Adopted by the AFL-CIO Executive Council, 1970
    - Ten Years of Progress: A Report on Israel, 1958
    - Tent City...Home of the Brave, undated
    - To Meet the People's Needs, 1966
    - Untitled articles (possibly galleys)
    - Viewpoint, 1975
    - Voici l'A.F.L.-C.I.O. (Here Is the A.F.L.-C.I.O.), undated
    - Who Is the Imperialist?, circa 1951, 1971
    - The World's Refugees: A Challenge to America, 1959
  - The American Forum, "What Can We Accomplish by the Khrushchev Visit?," "The Khrushchev Visit," "The Effects of the Khrushchev Visit," "The Controversy Over Our Space Program,", 1959 September, October (Box 21)
  - American Friends of the Captive Nations, Questions and Answers on the Berlin Crisis, 1959 July
  - The American Heart, published by the American Heart Association, 1950
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development
    - The AIFLD Report, 1967 March
    - The American Institute for Free Labor Development, undated
    - Industrial Training Center, Georgetown, British Guiana, 1965 September
    - Progress Report
      - circa 1965
      - circa 1966
      - 1967
      - 1969
      - 1970
    - Report on Activities, 1965 September
    - Report on Examination of Financial Statements, 1964 December 31
    - Social Action Projects, circa 1962
  - American Jewish Committee
    - Jews Behind the Iron Curtain, 1950 April
    - The Middle East Ferment, 1956 May
    - News from the Committee, 1973 October
    - Questions People Ask about Israel and America's National Interest, 1975 July
    - To the Counsellors of Peace, 1945 March
    - A World Charter for Human Rights, undated
  - American Jewish Congress, Law and Social Action, 1947 May-June
  - American Labor, 1969 December
  - The American Labor Monthly, 1924 February
  - American Labor News, 1949 May
  - American Labor Services for the U.N., Press Service, 1957 October
  - American Labor Weekly, 1927 July
  - American Labor's Role in Less Developed Countries, 1958 October
  - American Labour, 1968 June
  - American-Russian Institute
    - The U.S.S.R. at War, 1942
    - The U.S.S.R. in Reconstruction, 1944
  - American Security Council, undated
  - American Society for Russian Relief, USA-USSR: A Story of Friendship and Aid, 1941-1946, circa 1946
  - The American Tariff League, Monthly Bulletin, 1940 September-October
  - American Tract Society, Seven Red Soldiers Go Singing to Heaven, undated
  - American Workers Look at the Soviet Union, Impressions of the American Trade Union Delegation That Visited the Soviet Union in June and July, 1951
  - The American Workers Party, Toward an American Revolutionary Labor Movement, 1934
  - Americans United for World Organization, Here Comes Your Last Chance, undated
  - Amidon, Beulah, Jobs After Forty, 1939
  - Amory, Cleveland, Israel in Siege, 1970
  - Amter, Israel, The Truth About Finland, undated
  - Analysis of Current Chinese Communist Problems, Institute of International Relations, Republic of China (incomplete), 1962-1963 (Box 22)
  - L'Analytique hebdomadaire de la presse communiste (incomplete), 1963-1964
  - Anderson, Dewey, Water and Growth, New Factors - New Action, 1960 September
  - Andrew, A. Piatt, Our Prearmistice Loans, 1926 January 13
  - Ang Bantay, Official Organ of the Strikers, Honolulu, 1924 April
  - Anglo-Polish Review, 1951 October, November
  - The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1963 November, 1972 September
  - Annals of the Institute of Social Science, University of Tokyo, 1969
  - An Annotated Guide to Modern China, 1967 April
  - An Appeal to the Membership of the Socialist Party by the Revolutionary Policy Committee, 1934 March
  - Arbeit und Freiheit, 1961 December
  - Arbeiter-Zeitung, 1931 October 5
  - Arbeits - und Sozialrecht, 1948 July
  - Arendt, Hannah, The Ex-Communists, 1953 March 20
  - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, Neutrality: Varying Tunes, reprinted from Foreign Affairs, 1956 October
  - Aron, Raymond, The Meaning of Hungary, undated
  - Asher, Robert E., International Development and the U.S. National Interest, 1967 July
  - Asian Analysis (incomplete), 1972-1977
  - Asian Analyst (incomplete), 1959-1971 (Box 23)
  - Asian Labour, 1952 March
  - Asian Notes (incomplete), 1964-1971 (Box 24)
  - Asian Peoples' Anti-Communist League, Republic of China (Box 25)
    - Charts Concerning Chinese Communists on the Mainland, 1966
    - Communist Tyranny and People's Resistance on the Chinese Mainland During 1954, 1955
    - The Current Strategy and Tactics of International Communism, 1955